Haipeng Yu January 2021

CONTACT Information 239B Kildee Hall Iowa State University Ames, Iowa 50011 USA E-mail: hpyu@iastate.edu Phone: (701) 730-1368 WWW: haipengu.github.io

RESEARCH INTERESTS

My overarching research interest is to understand the genotype-phenotype map in animals and plants using computational and statistical genetics. Particularly, I am interested in developing and applying statistical methods to the whole-genome prediction of complex traits, genome-wide association analysis, high-throughput phenotyping analysis, and image analysis.

EDUCATION

Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Virginia USA

Ph.D., Animal and Poultry Sciences - Quantitative Genetics, May 2020

- Dissertation: "Designing and modeling high-throughput phenotyping data in quantitative genetics" [Virginia Tech Libraries]
- Advisor: Dr. Gota Morota

North Dakota State University, Fargo, North Dakota USA

M.S., Animal Breeding and Genetics, August 2016

- Thesis: "The exploration of a four-platform standing scale in the application of measuring temperament in beef cattle"
- Advisor: Dr. Lauren Hulsman Hanna

Qingdao Agricultural University, Qingdao, Shandong CHINA

B.S., Veterinary Medicine, July 2013

Professional Positions

Department of Animal Science

Iowa State University, Ames, Iowa USA

• Post-doctoral Fellow

08/2020 - Present

Work Experience

Department of Animal and Poultry Sciences

Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Virginia USA

• Graduate Research Assistant

08/2018 - 05/2020

• Graduate Teaching Assistant

Spring, 2019 and 2020

Department of Animal Science

University of Nebraska-Lincoln, Lincoln, Nebraska USA

• Graduate Research Assistant

08/2016 - 08/2018

Department of Animal Sciences

North Dakota State University, Fargo, North Dakota USA

• Graduate Research Assistant

01/2015 - 05/2016

Professional society memberships • The American Society of Animal Science. 2017 - Present

Preprints

- 10. Campbell M, <u>Yu H</u>, Momen M, and Morota G. Examining the relationships between phenotypic plasticity and local environments with genomic structural equation models. *bioRxiv*. doi: 10.1101/2019.12.11.873257
 - 9. Yu H and Morota G. GCA: An R package for genetic connectedness analysis using pedigree and genomic data. *bioRxiv*. doi: 10.1101/696419

PEER REVIEWED
JOURNAL PAPERS

4 first author and 4 co-author

2021

- 8. Pegolo S, <u>Yu H</u>, Morota G, Bisutti V, Rosa GJM, Bittante G, and Cecchinato A. Structural equation modelling for unravelling the multivariate genomic architecture of milk proteins in dairy cattle. *Journal of Dairy Science*. In press.
- 7. Momen M, Bhatta M, Hussain W, <u>Yu H</u>, and Morota G. Modeling multiple phenotypes in wheat using data-driven genomic exploratory factor analysis and Bayesian network learning. *Plant Direct*. In press.

2020

- **6.** Amorim ST, <u>Yu H</u>, Momen M, de Albuquerque, LG, Pereira, ASC, Baldi F, and Morota G. An assessment of genomic connectedness measures in Nellore cattle. *Journal of Animal Science*. Early view. doi: 10.1093/jas/skaa289
- 5. <u>Yu H</u>, Morota G, Celestino EF, Dahlen CR, Wagner SA, Riley DG, and Hanna LLH. Deciphering cattle temperament measures derived from a four-platform standing scale using genetic factor analytic modeling. *Frontiers in Genetics*. doi: 10.3389/fgene.2020.00599

2019

- 4. Hanna LLH, Hieber JK, <u>Yu H</u>, Celestino Jr EF, Dahlen CR, Wagner SA, and Riley DG. 2019. Blood collection has negligible impact on scoring temperament in Angus-based weaned calves. *Livestock Science*. **230**:103835. doi: 10.1016/j.livsci.2019.103835
- 3. <u>Yu H</u>, Campbell MT, Zhang Q, Walia H, and Morota G. 2019. Genomic Bayesian confirmatory factor analysis and Bayesian network to characterize a wide spectrum of rice phenotypes. *G3: Genes, Genomes, Genetics.* **9**:1975-1986. doi: 10.1534/g3.119.400154

2018

2. <u>Yu H</u>, Spangler ML, Lewis RM, and Morota G. 2018. Do stronger measures of genomic connectedness enhance prediction accuracies across management units? *Journal of Animal Science*. **96**:4490-4500. doi: 10.1093/jas/sky316

2017

1. <u>Yu H</u>, Spangler ML, Lewis RM, and Morota G. 2017. Genomic relatedness strengthens genetic connectedness across management units. *G3: Genes, Genomes, Genetics.* 10:3543-3556. doi: 10.1534/g3.117.300151.

Papers in Proceedings

1 first author

2018

Yu H, Spangler ML, Lewis RM, and Morota G. 2018. Stronger measures of genomic connectedness enhance prediction accuracies across management units. In: *Proceedings*, 11th World Congress of Genetics Applied to Livestock Production. 11:406. February 11-16, Auckland, New Zealand. [PDF]

CONTRIBUTED PRESENTATIONS

2020

- **6**. Development of image analysis pipeline to predict body weight in pigs. EAAP Annual Meeting 2020. Online. December 3.
- 5. Development of image analysis pipeline to predict body weight in pigs. ASAS-CSAS-WSASAS Virtual Annual Meeting and Trade Show. Online. July 19-23.

2019

4. Precision agriculture on cattle temperament: Utilizing factor analysis and multi-trait modeling to characterize a four-platform standing scale. NCERA-225 Annual Meeting. Implementation and Strategies for National Beef Cattle Genetic Evaluation. Blacksburg, VA. October 10-11.

2018

3. An assessment of genomic relatedness across management units. ADSA-ASAS 2018 Midwest Meeting. Omaha, NE. March 12-14. [Abstract]

2017

- Stronger measures of genomic connectedness enhance prediction accuracies across management units. NCERA-225 Annual Meeting. Implementation and Strategies for National Beef Cattle Genetic Evaluation. Stanley Stout Livestock Marketing Center, Manhattan, KS. October 18-19.
- 1. Genomic relatedness strengthens genetic connectedness across management units. ASAS-CSAS Annual Meeting and Trade Show. Baltimore, MD. July 8-12.

Intramural Seminars

2020

- Animal Breeding and Genetics Graduate Student Organization seminar. Department of Animal Science, Iowa State University. October 2.
- Animal Breeding and Genetics seminar. Department of Animal Science, Iowa State University. September 18.
- Ph.D. Thesis Defense. Department of Animal and Poultry Sciences, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University. March 18.

2019

- Ninth Annual Animal and Poultry Sciences Research Symposium. Department of Animal and Poultry Sciences, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University. May 21.
- The Reproductive Biology Club. Department of Animal and Poultry Sciences, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University. April 19.

2018

 Animal Breeding and Genetics seminar. Department of Animal Science, University of Nebraska-Lincoln. February 28.

2017

- Animal Breeding and Genetics seminar. Department of Animal Science, University of Nebraska-Lincoln. February 14.
- Animal Breeding and Genetics Seminars. Department of Animal Sciences, University of Nebraska-Lincoln. September 29.

2016

• M.S., Thesis Defense. Department of Animal Sciences, North Dakota State University. May 17.

Teaching

Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Virginia, USA

Guest Instructor

• GWAS Workshop [Slide]

Summer 2019

Graduate Teaching Assistant

• APSC 5984/20816: Complex Trait Genomics [WWW]

Spring 2020

• ALS 3104: Animal Breeding and Genetics

Spring 2019

University of Nebraska-Lincoln, Lincoln, Nebraska, USA

Guest Instructor

• ASCI 944 / STAT 844 Quantitative Methods for Genomics of Complex Traits [Slide] [R]

Spring 2018

North Dakota State University, Fargo, North Dakota USA Graduate Teaching Assistant

ANSC 357: Animal Genetics

Spring 2016

• AGRI 189: Skills for Academic Success

Fall 2015

OSS

CONTRIBUTIONS

R package

• GCA - https://github.com/HaipengU/GCA

PARTICIPATION IN MEETINGS, SYMPOSIUMS, AND WORKSHOPS

2020 • The 6th International Conference of Quantitative Genetics. Online. November 2-12. • The 2020 PigGen Canada-LSARP Virtual Workshop section II. Online. October 21. • The 2020 PigGen Canada-LSARP Virtual Workshop section I. Online. October 1. 2015 • NCERA-225 Annual Meeting. Implementation and Strategies for National Beef Cattle Genetic Evaluation. North Dakota State University, ND, October 22-23. • Graduate Learning Conference for College Teaching. North Dakota State University, ND. August 17-18. • WERA-1: Beef Cattle Breeding in the Western Region. Miles City, MT. May 19-20. • Midwest Meeting of erican Society of Animal Science. Des Moines, IA. March 15-18. Honors/ Awards 2020 • The 6th International Conference of Quantitative Genetics US-Based Early Career Researcher Scholarship. Online. November. 2019 • 24th Summer Institute in Statistical Genetics (SISG) Scholarship, University of Washington, July. • Ninth Annual Animal and Poultry Sciences Research Symposium Travel Award \$400, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, May. • Frank Bain Graduate Student Scholarship \$1,650, North Dakota State University, Spring. 2015 2009-2013 • Outstanding Undergraduate Scholarship, Qingdao Agricultural University, China. Additional TRAINING 2019 • Deep Learning for Computer Vision Workshop, Virginia Tech, VA, September 6. • 24th Summer Institute in Statistical Genetics (SISG), University of Washington, Seattle, WA,

- 24th Summer Institute in Statistical Genetics (SISG), University of Washington, Seattle, WA, July 17-24.
- Progrming and Computer Algorithms in Animal Breeding With Focus on Genomic Selection and Single-Step GBLUP, University of Georgia, GA, May 7-25.
- Introduction to Graphical Models With Applications to Quantitative Genetics and Genomics, Iowa State University, IA, June 19-23.
- Software Carpentry Workshop. University of Nebraska-Lincoln, NE, January 5-6.

2018

2017

REFERENCES References and additional information available upon request.